Guide to the Nils Arne Bendtz Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Nils Arne Bendtz Papers
1927-2003
1953-1990
RG 202
Yale University Divinity School Library
9
(19 boxes)
This collection documents the life and work of Lutheran theologian and ecumenist Nils Arne Bendtz. Bendtz received his B.D. and Ph.D. from Yale. He served as a missionary in China under the Board of Swedish Missions, with prisoners of war during World War II under the YMCA World's Committee, in Sumatra under the Commission of Younger Churches and Orphaned Missions of the National Lutheran Council, as a professor at Augustana Theological Seminary, as a pastor at Salem Evangelical Lutheran Church in Brooklyn, NY, and for the Lutheran World Federation.
Bendtz, Nils Arne
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of N. Arne Bendtz, 2004
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1930-1990, n.d.
II. Writings, 1947-1990, n.d
III. Documentation of Activities, 1942-1984, n.d.
IV. Collected Material, 1927-1990
V. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1931-1991
Biographical / Historical
1914 October 2 Nils Arne Bendtz born in Stockholm, Sweden, son of Nils T. and Emma Bendtz
1933-1935 Attended Inner Mission Bible College and Lutheran Independent Theological Seminary, Oslo, Norway
1935-1936 Attended China Inland Mission College, London
1936-1941 Served as missionary in China under the Swedish Board of Missions
1942-1946 Director of War Prisoners Aid of the World's Committee YMCA in China
1944-1946 General Secretary of Christian Welfare Association among Korean refugees in China
1946 Married Elsa L. Linne
1949 B.D. cum laude from Yale Divinity School
1949-1950 McFadden Fellow at Union Theological Seminary, New York
1952-1957 Served the Batak Church, Sumatra, including as Liaison Office between Lutheran World Federation and Indonesia and Professor of Theology in seminary. Helped to found Nommensen University, the first Lutheran university in Far East.
1953 Ph.D., Yale University - Thesis: "The Meaning of Luther's Doctrine of Forgiveness"
1957 Returned to the U.S. from Indonesia due to health reason, served as guest lecturer at Augustana Theological Seminary, IL
1958 Field representative for Lutheran World Action of National Lutheran Council; visiting across the U.S. and in Colombia and Ecuador
1958-1959 Professor of Systematic Theology at Pacific Lutheran Theological Seminary, CA
1961 Married Britt M. Friman; one son - Nils Arne Bendtz, Jr.
1964-1971 Pastor of Salem Evangelical Lutheran Church, Brooklyn, NY
1965-1971 Superintendent, Leif Ericson Day School, Brooklyn, NY
1966-1971 Adjunct Full Professor, Department of Anthropology and Sociology, Long Island University, Brooklyn, NY
1990s Director, International Management-Education Foundation, Honolulu, Hawaii
2006 Died
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the life and work of Lutheran theologian and ecumenist N. Arne Bendtz.
Series I, Correspondence is divided into five subseries: Professional / work-related correspondence of Bendtz, Personal correspondence of Bendtz, Family correspondence, Correspondence of others, and Swedish language correspondence. Of most interest in this series are the letters related to Bendtz's work with the National Lutheran Council and when he was stationed in Indonesia.
Series II, Writings, consists primarily of unpublished typescript writings by Bendtz on subjects related to theology and missions, but also includes some writings of others, including "A History of Augustana Foreign Mission" by Dr. Eric Wahlstrom.
Series III, Documentation of Activities, includes printed material, minutes, reports, etc. regarding organizations with which Bendtz was involved.. These materials should be considered in connection with correspondence from the same era.
Series IV, Collected Material, includes materials not specifically associated with Bendtz's work, but which he had collected over the years.
Series V, Personal Items and Memorabilia, includes biographical information and clippings re. Bendtz as well as photographs.
Lutheran Church -- Missions; Missions -- Indonesia; Educators; Missionaries
- Correspondence, 1930-1990, no date; Series I
  - Professional correspondence
    - Including regarding Yale Divinity School, 1930-1946 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Including regarding Yale Divinity School, Tracy Strong, 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Including regarding Yale Divinity School, 1950-1953 Apr (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Including regarding Yale Graduate School, ﻿1953 May-1954 Apr (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Incl. letter of introduction of Bendtz to Harold E. Stassen, Director, Foreign Operations Administration, Washington, DC, 1954 May-1955 Feb (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Including regarding Fridtjov Birkeli, ﻿1955 Mar- 1955Aug (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Including regarding Arne Sovik, ﻿1955 Sep- 1955Dec (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Including regarding Fridtjov Birkeli, ﻿1956 Jan- 1956 Sep (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Bendtz to/from others, ﻿1956 Nov.- 1957 Nov. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Including regarding Committee on Latin America of the Lutheran World Federation, ﻿1958 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Bendtz to/from others, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Bendtz to/from others, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Bendtz to/from others, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Including regarding National Lutheran Council, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Bendtz to/from others, ﻿1963 Jan- 1963Apr (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Bendtz to/from others, 1963﻿ May- 1963 Dec (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Including regarding Salem Oratorio Choir, 1964 ﻿Jan- Jun (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Including regarding Salem Oratorio Choir, ﻿ 1964 Jul- Dec (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Including regarding Salem Oratorio Choir, Midsummer Day Festival, ﻿1965 Jan- May (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Including regarding Midsummer Day Festival, ﻿ 1965 Jun-Aug (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Including regarding Midsummer Day Festival, 1965 ﻿Sep- Dec (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Including regarding J.O.I.N., Midsummer Day Festival, Danderyd Oratorio Choir and The Sofia Flickorna (Sofia Girls), ﻿ 1966 Jan-May (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Including regarding J.O.I.N., Midsummer Day Festival, Danderyd Oratorio Choir and The Sofia Flickorna (Sofia Girls), ﻿ 1966 Jun-Aug (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Including regarding Midsummer Day Festival, Danderyd Oratorio Choir and The Sofia Flickorna (Sofia Girls), 1966﻿ Sep- Dec (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Bendtz to/from others, 1967﻿ Jan- Apr (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Bendtz to/from others, ﻿1967 May- Jun (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Bendtz to/from others, ﻿1967 July- Dec (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Including regarding Manpower and Career Development Agency, 1968﻿ Jan-Oct (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Bendtz to/from others, ﻿1968 Nov.- 1969 Dec. (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Including regarding Midsummer Day Festival, ﻿ 1970 Jan- Jul (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Bendtz to/from others, ﻿1970 Aug.- 1971 Jan (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Including regarding Metropolitan New York, ﻿1971 Feb- Apr (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Bendtz to/from others, ﻿1971 May-Dec (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Bendtz to/from others, ﻿1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Including regarding Jarvis Rental of Gallery, ﻿1974-1977 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Including regarding Jarvis Rental of Gallery﻿, ﻿1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Including regarding CET Language Program, ﻿1980-1984 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Including regarding Shatemuck Realty Company, ﻿1984-1986 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Including regarding Shatemuck Realty Company, ﻿1987- 1989 Apr (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Bendtz to/from others, 1989 ﻿May -1990 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - ﻿Partial/ Not dated, no date (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Personal correspondence
    - To/from friends and acquaintances, ﻿1930-1959 (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - To/from friends and acquaintances, ﻿1960-1963 (Box 6, Folder 43)
    - To/from friends and acquaintances, ﻿1964-1969 (Box 6, Folder 44)
    - To/from friends and acquaintances, ﻿1970-1979 (Box 6, Folder 45)
    - To/from friends and acquaintances, ﻿1980-1988 (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - To/from friends and acquaintances, ﻿1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - To/from friends and acquaintances, ﻿no date (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Family correspondence
    - Arne Bendtz to and from family
      - Elsa Linne Bendtz to and from Arne Bendtz, ﻿1953-1956,no date (Box 7, Folder 49)
      - ﻿Britt Bendtz, Arne Jr., ﻿1971-1982 (Box 7, Folder 50)
      - ﻿Jerry Walter Bendtz materials: Correspondence, Last will and testament, Insurance policy, ﻿1953-1967 (Box 7, Folder 51)
    - Correspondence of family members (not to/from Arne Bendtz)
      - ﻿Elsa Linne Bendtz: References, yearbook, ﻿1921-1951 (Box 7, Folder 52)
      - ﻿Elsa Linne Bendtz: correspondence about travels, ﻿1953-1954 (Box 7, Folder 53)
      - Elsa Linne Bendtz: correspondence about travels, ﻿1955-1957, no date (Box 7, Folder 54)
      - ﻿Elsa Linne Bendtz: Writings and poetry, no date (Box 7, Folder 55)
  - Correspondence of others
    - Not to/from Arne Bendtz, not to family members, ﻿1945-1989, no date (Box 7, Folder 56)
  - ﻿Swedish language correspondence
    - Bendtz to/from others, 1930-1949 (Box 8, Folder 57)
    - Bendtz to/from others, 1950-1959 (Box 8, Folder 58)
    - Bendtz to/from others, ﻿1960-1961 (Box 8, Folder 59)
    - Bendtz to/from others, ﻿1962-1965 (Box 8, Folder 60)
    - Bendtz to/from others, ﻿1966-1969 (Box 8, Folder 61)
    - Bendtz to/from others, ﻿1970-1979 (Box 8, Folder 62)
    - Bendtz to/from others, ﻿1980-1990, no date (Box 8, Folder 63)
- Writings, 1947-1990, no date
  - Writings by Bendtz
    - "﻿Nommensen and Kierkegaard: An Attempt at Comparing the Sense of Vocation of Two of the Most Profound Christians of the Nineteenth Century", no date (Box 9, Folder 64)
    - "About Bataks and Their Church", no date (Box 9, Folder 65)
    - ﻿"Acts", ﻿no date (Box 9, Folder 66)
    - ﻿"Autonomy defined", no date (Box 9, Folder 67)
    - ﻿"Bendtz' Papers", Various writings, no date (Box 9, Folder 68)
    - ﻿"Dissertations", no date (Box 9, Folder 69)
    - ﻿"Faith and Knowledge in Luther's Theology", no date (Box 9, Folder 70)
    - ﻿"General Theories and Practices of Leadership", no date (Box 9, Folder 71)
    - ﻿"Genesis", ﻿no date (Box 9, Folder 72)
    - ﻿"Genesis", no date (Box 9, Folder 73)
    - ﻿"Gospel of John", no date (Box 9, Folder 74)
    - ﻿"Indonesia- Dialogue and Friendship", "God's Compassion in Action", "The Soul Care of the Roman Catholic Church and its Challenges to our Church", "Faith of the Batak", "The Role of Lutheran Unity in Missions", "The Mission Method of Group conversion and the Pietistic Individualism", no date (Box 9, Folder 75)
    - ﻿" A Responsible Church Faces a Diverse Society", ﻿1962 (Box 10, Folder 76)
    - ﻿"Studies of Moral Life", no date (Box 10, Folder 77)
    - ﻿Notes, Sermons, Lectures, Essays, ﻿no date (Box 10, Folder 78)
    - ﻿"The Theological Basis for a Consideration of the Economic Order and the Life of the Church", "Effective and Ineffective Groups", no date (Box 10, Folder 79)
    - ﻿Class work: "What is Social Ethics?", "Structure", "The Negro Problem in America and Its Relation to the Race Problem in World Politics", 1948,1949﻿ no date (Box 10, Folder 80)
    - ﻿"World Service", no date (Box 10, Folder 81)
  - Swedish language materials
    - Writings, no date (Box 10, Folder 82)
    - Writings, ﻿no date (Box 10, Folder 83)
  - Untitled
    - Misc. notes, no date (Box 11, Folder 84)
    - ﻿Lectures, notes, essays, no date (Box 11, Folder 85)
    - ﻿Lectures, notes, essays, no date (Box 11, Folder 86)
    - ﻿Lectures, notes, essays, no date (Box 11, Folder 87)
    - ﻿Lectures, notes, essays, ﻿1958-1959 (Box 11, Folder 88)
    - ﻿Lecture notes for "Christian Ethics" class, no date (Box 11, Folder 90)
    - ﻿Lecture notes for "Structure of Religion" class, no date (Box 11, Folder 91)
  - Writings by others
    - ﻿"The Problems and Promises of Maphilindo" by Paul B. Pedersen, and various writings by this author, ﻿no date (Box 12, Folder 92)
    - ﻿"Jajasan Seni Rakjat Indonesia, "Serindo"" by Paul B. Pedersen, and other writings by same author, ﻿1967, no date (Box 12, Folder 93)
    - ﻿"Teacher Education in Indonesia" by Mrs. Corinne H. Bruning, and other writings, ﻿1967, no date (Box 12, Folder 94)
    - ﻿Student papers, ﻿1947, 1962-1963 (Box 12, Folder 95)
    - ﻿Student papers, ﻿1954-1990 (Box 12, Folder 96)
    - ﻿"A History of Augustana Foreign Mission" by Dr. Eric Wahlstrom, no date (Box 13, Folder 97)
    - ﻿Materials used for Bendtz' research of Indonesia, no date (Box 13, Folder 98)
- Documentation of Activities, 1942-1984, no date
  - Work related
    - ﻿"Bay Ridge Ecumenical Activities", ﻿1967-1971 (Box 14, Folder 99)
    - ﻿Bay Ridge Lutheran Clergy: Meeting minutes, ﻿1966 (Box 14, Folder 100)
    - ﻿Bedford Stuyvesant Advisory Board: Member's listing, ﻿1966 (Box 14, Folder 101)
    - ﻿CAPP: Center for Attacking Pervasive Poverty in Rural Villages of Tropical Areas: Report, no date (Box 14, Folder 102)
    - ﻿Christian University of Sumatra: Meeting minutes, no date (Box 14, Folder 103)
    - ﻿Chicago Theological Seminary: Meeting minutes, ﻿1954 (Box 14, Folder 104)
    - ﻿Community Development Agency: Guidelines, ﻿1967 (Box 14, Folder 105)
    - ﻿I.M.P.R.O.V.E.: Research report, ﻿1966 (Box 14, Folder 106)
    - ﻿J.O.I.N.: Job Orientation in Neighborhoods: Proposals, reports, minutes, etc., ﻿1965-1966 (Box 14, Folder 107)
    - ﻿Leif Ericson Day School: Charter and By-laws, meeting minutes, ﻿1973, no date (Box 14, Folder 108)
    - ﻿Kingston Lutheran Council: Meeting minutes, ﻿1974 (Box 14, Folder 109)
    - ﻿Lutheran Committee on Housing: Meeting minutes, ﻿1965 (Box 14, Folder 110)
    - ﻿Lutheran Foreign Missions Conference of North America: Memo﻿, ﻿1963 (Box 14, Folder 111)
    - ﻿Lutheran Theological Seminary: Continuing Cultivation Committee Manual, no date (Box 14, Folder 112)
    - ﻿Lutheran World Federation: Application, meeting agenda, ﻿1971 (Box 14, Folder 113)
    - ﻿Manpower Builders Inc.: Training manual, minutes, etc., ﻿1968 (Box 14, Folder 114)
    - ﻿Midwest Fellowship of Professions of Missions: Minutes, ﻿1962 (Box 14, Folder 115)
    - ﻿National Lutheran Council: Meeting minutes, agenda, ﻿1951-1954 (Box 14, Folder 116)
    - ﻿New York City Council Against Poverty: Goals and guidelines for proposal submission, ﻿1967-1968 (Box 14, Folder 117)
    - ﻿Nommensen University: Reports, ﻿1974, 1984 (Box 14, Folder 118)
    - ﻿Protestant Church of the Batu Islands, The: Meeting minutes, ﻿1954 (Box 15, Folder 119)
    - ﻿St. Paul's Lutheran Church: Meeting agenda, ﻿1981-1982 (Box 15, Folder 120)
    - ﻿Salem Lutheran Church: Meeting agendas, Pastoral reports, etc., ﻿1954-1967 (Box 15, Folder 121)
    - ﻿Salem Lutheran Church: Reports, agendas, etc., ﻿1968-1971 (Box 15, Folder 122)
    - ﻿Sweden Day Committee: Meeting minutes, ﻿1967 (Box 15, Folder 123)
    - ﻿Y.M.C.A.: China Prisoners' of War reports, ﻿1942-1944 (Box 15, Folder 124)
    - ﻿Y.M.C.A.: China Prisoners' of War reports, ﻿1945-1971, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 125)
    - ﻿Course syllabi, ﻿1962-1971, no date (Box 15, Folder 126)
- Collected material, 1927-1990
  - ﻿Newspaper clippings, pamphlets, etc.
    - ﻿Various materials: Pamphlets, flyers, programs, business cards, Sweden Day materials, Salem Oratorio Choir materials, ﻿1963-1989 (Box 16, Folder 127)
    - ﻿Various materials: Pamphlets, brochures, Book of hymns, manuals, etc., ﻿1956-1962 (Box 16, Folder 128)
    - ﻿Various materials: Pamphlets, brochures, etc., ﻿1953-1989 (Box 16, Folder 129)
    - ﻿Various materials: Swedish language, ﻿1927-1981 (Box 16, Folder 130)
    - ﻿Various materials: "Neem Tree Project", ﻿1990 (Box 17, Folder 131)
    - ﻿The Prophet, ﻿1957-1958, 1960 (Box 17, Folder 132)
    - ﻿Newspaper clippings: General clippings about Bendtz, ﻿1954-1970 (Box 17, Folder 133)
    - ﻿Newspaper clippings: General clippings about Bendtz, some in Swedish language, ﻿1954-1961, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 134)
    - ﻿Newspaper clippings: Bendtz' family, ﻿1966, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 135)
    - ﻿Newspaper clippings: Concerning Bay Ridge, ﻿1964-1972 (Box 17, Folder 136)
    - ﻿Newspaper clippings: Leif Ericson School, Sweden Day, some in Swedish language, ﻿1966-1972 (Box 17, Folder 137)
    - ﻿Newspaper clippings: Salem Lutheran Church, ﻿1965-1971 (Box 17, Folder 138)
    - ﻿Newspaper Clippings: Sofia Girls, Danderyd Choir, some in Swedish language, ﻿1966-1969 (Box 17, Folder 139)
    - ﻿Newspaper Clippings: (non- English), ﻿1961-1966 (Box 17, Folder 140)
    - ﻿Newspaper Clippings: not about Bendtz, some articles in Swedish language, ﻿1956-1989 (Box 17, Folder 141)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1931-1991, no date
  - Biographical material and resume, no date (Box 18, Folder 142)
  - ﻿Greeting cards, ﻿1961-1975 (Box 18, Folder 143)
  - ﻿Guest books, no date (Box 18, Folder 144)
  - ﻿Health records, life insurance documents, ﻿1945-1981 (Box 18, Folder 145)
  - ﻿Various certificates: Verifications, Visa applications, ﻿1945-1978 (Box 18, Folder 146)
  - ﻿Various materials: Yale Divinity School Grades, parking ticket claim, etc. Some material in Swedish language, ﻿1931-1982 (Box 18, Folder 147)
  - ﻿Financial information: Receipts, bills, ﻿1943-1991, no date (Box 18, Folder 148)
  - ﻿Photographs: Elsa Linne Bendtz, Sofia Girls, Bendtz and others, ﻿1989, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 149)
  - ﻿Photographs: Sofia Girls, Danderyd Choir, Bendtz, etc., ﻿1943-1967 (Box 19, Folder 150)
  - ﻿Photographs: Bendtz and students, ﻿1966-1971 (Box 19, Folder 151)
  - ﻿Photographs: Bendtz, Ruth Ericsson (director of Danderyd Choir), Lutheran School of Theology class photos, etc., ﻿1963-1967, no date. (Box 19, Folder 152)
  - ﻿Photographs: Church of Good Shepherd Confirmation class photo, ﻿1950 (Box 19, Folder 153)